

NICOLÒ PAGAN, Ph.D. ETH

ABOUT ME

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I have a strong passion for mathematical modelling of real-world problems using numerical simulations and generative AI. My primary research interests lie in the area of algorithmic fairness, where I explore the complex interplay between AI and human decision-making so that I can design effective long-term interventions that foster social well-being.

KFYWORDS

Contact nicolo.pagan@uzh.ch | +41 (0)78 9458438 | (he/him) Website https://nicolo-pagan.github.io/







EXPERIENCE

ACADEMIC

05 / 2021 - Present Postdoctoral Researcher, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics,

University of Zurich

Mentor: Prof. Dr. Anikó Hannák

Postdoctoral Researcher, Social Networks Lab, Department of Humanities, 05 / 2021 - 11 / 2021

Social and Political Sciences, ETH Zurich

Mentor: Prof. Dr. Christoph Stadtfeld

02 / 2021 - 05 / 2021 Lecturer, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics, University of

Zurich

PROFESSIONAL

05 / 2013 - 12 / 2015 Software Engineer and Research Consultant in Computational Fluid-

Dynamics (CFD). Ascomp AG (Zürich, Switzerland).

07 / 2012 - 08 / 2012 **Software Engineer Intern** at FLUXiM AG (Winterthur, Switzerland)

EDUCATION

2016 - 2021 Ph.D., Automatic Control Laboratory, Department of Information Technology and

Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich

Thesis: Modeling, analysis, and inference in social network formation

Advisor: Prof. Dr. Florian Dörfler

2011 - 2013 M.Sc. in Computational Science and Engineering (5.45/6), EPF Lausanne

Thesis Coupling 1D system code OLGA with TransAT CFD

Advisors Prof. Dr. François Gallaire, Dr. Sylvain Reboux

2007 - 2010 **B.Sc. in Mathematical Engineering** (110/110 cum Laude), Politecnico di Torino

Thesis Analysis of the car behaviour while transiting on an active speed bump

Advisor Prof. Dr. Luigi Preziosi

PUBLICATIONS

SELECTED

- N. Pagan*, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: <u>A</u>

 <u>Classification of Feedback Loops and Their Relation to Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems</u>. 3rd ACM Conference on Equity and Access in Algorithms,
- 2021 Mechanisms, and Optimization (EAAMO '23).
- **N. Pagan**, W. Mei, C. Li, and F. Dörfler. <u>A meritocratic network formation model for the</u>
 2019 <u>rise of social media influencers</u>. *Nature Communications 12*, 6865 (2021).
- **N. Pagan**, and F. Dörfler. <u>Game theoretical inference of human behavior in social networks.</u> *Nature Communications 10*, 5507 (2019).

GRANTS

01 / 2022 - 12 / 2023 Ethical Auditing of Control Systems Methods, Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF). Grant #180545. CHF 192'000.

HONORS AND AWARDS

2020	Featured in the Top 50 Physics Articles in Nature Communications
2019	Invited by the Department of Mathematical Sciences at Politecnico di Torino
	during the Department of Excellence 2018-2022 program: awarded a scholarship
2011	Erasmus program at EPF Lausanne. Awarded a scholarship
2010	Admitted to the 7th cycle of Alta Scuola Politecnica Educational program
2007	Rank 1st at the Engineering admission test at Politecnico di Torino: awarded a
	scholarship
2007	High School Diploma: awarded with special distinction and a scholarship

INVITED TALKS

00 / 04 / 0000	Christiania Internationa amang Casial Madia Cantant Craatan Madalahan an
03 / 04 / 2023	Strategic Interactions among Social Media Content Creators, Workshop on
	Games on Networks, National University of Singapore.
28 / 02 / 2023	Social Computing: Bridging the Gap Between Technology and Human
	Interaction, Digital Society Initiative (DSI) Professors Presentations, Zürich.
01 / 09 / 2022	The Interplay Between Content Quality and Recommender Systems in Social
	Network Dynamics. Keynote at the Media Consumption Habits of Young People
	workshop, European Alliance of News Agencies (EANA), Zürich.
15/07/2021	A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers
	Doctoral course on Mining knowledge from complex network, Torino (online)
12 / 12 / 2020	A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers
	Dynamics in Social and Economic Networks, CDC, South Korea (online)
21 /09 / 2020	Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Autonomy
	Talk, IDSC, ETH Zurich (online).
09 /06 / 2020	Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Intelligent
	Control Seminar, Peking University (online).
28/11/2019	Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Workshop

on Networks Dynamics in the Social, Economic, and Financial Sciences, Torino.

TEACHING

2022	Examiner of Fundamentals of People Oriented Computing, Department of
	Informatics, University of Zurich
2021	Lecturer of Social Computing, Department of Informatics, University of Zurich
2019 - 2020	Head Teaching Assistant of Game Theory and Control, Department of
	Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich
2016 - 2019	Head Teaching Assistant of Linear Systems Theory, Department of Information
	Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich
2017 - 2018	Head Teaching Assistant of Non-linear Systems and Control, Department of
	Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich
2012	Teaching Assistant of Informatics 2, Department of Informatics, EPF Lausanne

SUPERVISING

10 / 2023 - present	Jiaqi Zhang, University of Zurich. Master Thesis: Using generative AI for modelling large-scale human behaviour for health notification interventions
03 / 2023 - 08 / 2023	Michael Blum, University of Zurich. Independent Study: How Specialization Shapes Pattern Recognition: Empirical Evidence from the Domain of Chess.
05 / 2022 - 05 / 2023	Maria Helena Margareta Pelli and Andrianos Michail, University of Zurich. Master Project: A longitudinal study of emotions on Twitter chains of re-tweets
03 / 2022 - 07 / 2022	Jules Authier, ETH Zurich. Semester Project: Analysis of the Closed-Loop between Recommender Systems and Opinion Dynamics
06 / 2021 - 11 / 2021	Michael Blum, University of Zurich. Bachelor Thesis: Learning and success in chess: the role of openings patterns
09 / 2020 - 04 / 2021	Anna M. Maddux, ETH Zurich. Master Thesis: Behavior estimation in dynamic games
05 / 2020 - 12 / 2020	Cheng Li, ETH Zurich. Master Thesis: <i>Data-driven analysis of the ranking-quality network formation model</i>
05 / 2017 - 08 / 2018	Marco Buob, ETH Zurich. Semester Project: Dynamics of cooperative agents in social network formation: theory and simulation
10 / 2017 - 02 / 2018	Tomer Gidron, ETH Zurich. Semester Project: Centrality games in social and economic networks
02 / 2015 - 08 / 2015	Jiadong Bao, ETH Zurich. Master Thesis at Ascomp AG: Cathare-TransAT Coupling for the Prediction of Boron Dilution in the ROCOM Test Facility
02 / 2014 - 08 / 2014	Hassan Bahramian, Politecnico di Milano. Master Thesis at ASCOMP AG: Coupling 1D System Code with TransAT CFD

REVIEW ACTIVITY

Journals	Nature Communications, Artificial Intelligence Reviews, Automatica, Chaos, Journal of Complex Networks, VLDB, IEEE Transactions on Control of Network
	Systems
Conferences	The Web Conference, International Conference on Computational Social Science
	(IC2S2), ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency
	(FAccT), Network Science Conference (NetSci), Complex Networks Conference,

European Control Conference (ECC), IFAC World Congress

Conference Organizer IC2S2 2022

INDEPENDENT COURSES

10/2	.021	AI + X Summit Workshop, Zürich
06/2	.020	Data Science in Techno-Socio-Economic Systems Workshop, ETH Zurich and
		NYU Courant (online)
11/2	019	Network Dynamics in the Social, Economic, and Financial Sciences Workshop,
		Politecnico di Torino
06/2	.018	Summer School on Economic Networks, Oxford
10/2	017	Autonomous Decision-Making Workshop, ETH Risk Center, Zürich

IT SKILLS

Software

Foundational	Programming	Data Science	Web Tools
MacOS-Unix	C / C++	Python/R	HTML
Windows OS	Bash	SQL/Pandas	CSS
MS Office	Fortran	TensorFlow	
liWork	Git	Tableau	

LANGUAGES

Mother Tongue Italian
Other Languages English C2 | French B1 | German A2

APPENDIX

Full list of publications List of conference talks

REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Anikó Hannák, Assistant Professor, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics, University of Zurich hannak@ifi.uzh.ch

Prof. Dr. Florian Dörfler, Associate Professor, Automatic Control Laboratory, Department of Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich dorfler@ethz.ch

PERSONAL INFO

APPENDIX A

FULL LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

[J3] S. Ioneuscu, A. Hannák, and N. Pagan: *The Role of Luck in the Success of Social Media Influencers*, Applied Network Science (2023). DOI:10.1007/s41109-023-00573-4

[J2] **N. Pagan,** W. Mei, C. Li, and F. Dörfler: *A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers*, Nature Communications 12, 6865 (2021) **DOI**:10.1038/s41467-021-27089-8

[J1] **N. Pagan** and F. Dörfler: *Game theoretical inference of human behavior in social networks*, Nature Communications 10, 5507 (2019). **DOI**:10.1038/s41467-019-13148-8

Conference Articles

[[C9] A. Bouleimen, **N. Pagan**, S. Cresci, A. Urman, and S. Giordano: *Dynamics of toxic behavior in the Covid-19 vaccination debate*. 12th International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications (Forthcoming). Manuscript available upon request.

C8] **N. Pagan***, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: A Classification of Feedback Loops and Their Relation to Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems, 3rd ACM Conference on Equity and Access in Algorithms, Mechanisms, and Optimization (EAAMO '23).

[C7] S. Ionescu, A. Hannák, and **N. Pagan**: <u>Group Fairness for Content Creators: the Role of Human and Algorithmic Biases under Popularity-based Recommendations</u>, 17th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems 2023.

[C6] N. Lanzetti, F. Dörfler, and N. Pagan: <u>The Impact of Recommendation Systems on Opinion Dynamics: Microscopic versus Macroscopic Effects</u>, 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) (2023).

[C5] A. Maddux, **N. Pagan**, G. Belgioioso, and F. Dörfler: *Data-Driven Behaviour Estimation in Parametric Games*, 22nd World Congress of the International Federation of Automatic Control (2023) **DOI**:10.48550/arXiv.2202.01229.

[C4] S. Ionescu, **N. Pagan**, and A. Hannák: *Individual Fairness for Social Media Influencers*, The 11th International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications (2022) **DOI**:10.1007/978-3-031-21127-0_14.

[C3] J. Bao, S. Reboux, **N. Pagan**, and D. Lakehal: *Cathare-TransAT Coupling for the Prediction of Boron Dilution in the ROCOM Test Facility*, 16th International Topical Meeting on Nuclear Reactor Thermal Hydraulics, (2015).

[C2] Labois, M., **N. Pagan**, D. Lakehal, and C. Narayanan: *Computational modelling of subsea hydrate formation and associated risks and impact on flow assurance,* In Proceeding of 10th International Conference on CFD in the Minerals and Process Industries. (2014)

[C1] S. Altazin, B. Perucco, N. Pagan, K. Lapagna, T. Lanz, R. Knaack, E. Knapp, B. Ruhstaller: *Multi-scale modeling of organic light-emitting devices*, SID Symposium Digest of Technical Papers (2013).

Conference Articles - Under Review

[C10] A. Michail*, M. H. M. Pelli*, A. M. Günster, and **N. Pagan**: *Emotions and Opinion Biases on Social Media: The Case of Abortion on Twitter*. Under review at The Web Conference 2024. Manuscript available upon request.

Manuscripts in Preparation

[J4] M. Blum and N. Pagan: How Specialization Shapes Pattern Recognition: Empirical Evidence from the Domain of Chess. Manuscript available upon request.

Extended Abstracts

[EA6] **N. Pagan***, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: *Closing the Loop: Feedback Loops and Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems*, 2nd European Workshop on Algorithmic Fairness (EWAF'23).

[EA5] **N. Pagan***, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: *Closing the Loop: Feedback Loops and Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems*, 9th International Conference on Computational Social Science (IC2S2) 2023.

[EA4] A. Bouleimen, **N. Pagan**, S. Cresci, A. Urman, G. Nogara, and S. Giordano: *User's Reaction Patterns in Online Social Network Communities*, the International School and Conference on Network Science (NetSci) (2023).

[EA3] S. Ionescu, A. Hannák, and **N. Pagan**: *The impact of users' homophily and recommendation biases on social network inequalities*, the International School and Conference on Network Science (NetSci) (2023).

[EA2] N. Pagan, W. Mei, and F. Dörfler: Emergence of Zipf's law among social networks influencers, IFAC Conference on Networked Systems (NecSys) (2022).

[EA1] **N. Pagan** and F. Dörfler: *Learning strategic behavior in social and economic networks*, The 7th International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications: book of abstracts, p.207-209 (2018).

Monograph

[Th1] **N. Pagan**: *Modeling, analysis, and inference in social network formation,* ETH Zurich Research Collection (2021). **DOI**: <u>10.3929/ethz-b-000501329</u>.

Media Coverage

[M3] <u>Mathematics: Investigating how social media influencers arise</u>, In: NatureAsia (2021).

[M2] What influences the rise of influencers?, In: Phys.org (2021).

[M1] N. Pagan Can social network structure reveal human behavior?, Behind the paper blog post at Behavioural and Social Sciences - Nature Research (2019).

APPENDIX B

LIST OF CONFERENCE TALKS

08 / 11 / 2022	Individual Fairness for Social Media Influencers, 11th International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications, Palermo (Italy)
08 / 09 / 2021	A meritocratic network formation model for User-Generated Content based platforms, 5th European Conference on Social Networks, Naples (Italy)
12 / 12 / 2018	Learning strategic behavior in social and economic networks, 7 th International Conference on Complex Networks, Cambridge (UK)
12 / 06 / 2018	Social network formation: from individual incentives to systemic stability, GameNet at NETSCI, Paris (France)
14/02/2018	From individuals decisions to emerging social structure, Infrastructure Resilience Conference, Zürich (Switzerland)